# 5550 Caddis Bend, Apt. 400 Fitchburg, WI, 53711 \$\pi +1(716)472-7283\$ □ pizzuto@wisc.edu □ apizzuto.github.io

# Alex Pizzuto

	Education
2017-present	(Expected) PhD, Physics, University of Wisconsin-Madison. Advisor: Justin Vandenbroucke
2017–2019	Master's of Arts, Physics, University of Wisconsin-Madison.  Minor: Computational methods in particle astrophysics
2013–2017	<b>Bachelor's of Science</b> , <i>Loyola University Chicago</i> , summa cum laude. Majors: Physics, Mathematics, Theoretical Physics and Applied Mathematics
	Research Overview
2017-present	<b>Realtime Neutrino Astronomy:</b> Developed pipelines to process low-latency data transferred via satellite to search for astrophysical neutrino sources
	Particle Astrophysics with IceCube: Implemented maximum likelihood analyses to search for neutrino sources from a variety of astrophysical source classes
	<b>The Distributed Electronic Cosmic-ray Observatory:</b> Maintained smartphone app that detects cosmic rays with cell phone camera image sensors
2015–2017	<b>Modified theories of gravity:</b> Explored analytic expressions of scalar fields near maximally rotating black holes in dynamical Chern-Simons gravity
	Awards and Fellowships
2020	Charles Elwood Mendenhall Research Award
2020	IceCube Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion travel grant (travel cancelled due to COVID-19)
2019	NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program Honorable Mention
2018	Teaching Assistant Rookie of the Year
2017	Barshall Incoming Graduate Fellowship
2017	Horan Award for Excellent Graduating Senior in Physics
2015–2017	Mulcahy Research Fellow
2013–2017	Full Tuition Presidential Scholarship
2013–2017	Member of Loyola Interdisciplinary Honors Program
2016	Lee Teng Fellowship in Accelerator Physics
2014, 2016	Father Gerst Memorial Award for Excellence in Physics
	Leadership, Public Outreach, and Community Involvement
2020-present	Astrobites contributing author For a list of articles, see https://astrobites.org/author/apizzuto/
2020-present	WIPAC High School Internship volunteer
2019-present	Organizer of weekly WIPAC graduate student seminar series

2018-present Volunteer at local community science outreach events (approx. 5 per year)

2020 SkypeAScientist Participant

2019–2020 Physics graduate student peer mentor

# Teaching Experience

2020 University of Wisconsin-Madison, Grader.

Physics 772: Particle Astrophysics

2017 University of Wisconsin-Madison, Teaching Assistant.

Physics 202: Electricity & Magnetism for Engineers

2014–2017 **Loyola University Chicago**, *Teaching Assistant*.

Physics 111 (111L): Introductory Mechanics (Lab), Physics 112 (112L): Introductory Electricity & Magnetism (Lab), Physics 301: Mathematical Methods of Physics

2016 Loyola University Chicago, Grader.

Physics 351: Electricity & Magnetism

# Mentoring Experience

2018-present Runze Li, UW-Madison undergraduate student: Effects of the geomagnetic field on cosmic-ray muons in ice; Simulation studies of the Distributed Electronic Cosmic-ray Observatory

2019–2020 Blake Gallay, visiting Cornell undergraduate student: Distributed Electronic Cosmic-ray Observatory updates and noise studies

#### Invited Talks

#### Colloquia

November Cosmic messengers from the extreme universe, Loyola University Chicago Physics depart-2019 ment colloquium

#### **Seminars**

February How to read an academic article, UW-Madison Physics professional development seminar 2020 series (slides)

#### **Schools**

June 2020 Frequentist and Bayesian Statistics, IceCube Bootcamp 2020 (virtual, slides)

June 2019 Introduction to Machine Learning in IceCube, IceCube Bootcamp 2019, Madison, WI (slides)

# Conferences, Meetings, and Workshops

#### Plenary Talks

September IceCube Fast Response Analysis: Results and Future Outlook, IceCube Fall Collaboration

2019 Meeting, Chiba, Japan

May 2019 Joint interpretation of anomalous ANITA events, IceCube Spring Collaboration Meeting, Madison, WI

#### Parallel Talks

June 2020 Search for sub-TeV neutrinos from novae, American Astronomical Society Meeting 236 (virtual)

- April 2020 Constraints on astrophysical interpretations of anomalous ANITA events with IceCube, American Physical Society April Meeting (virtual)
- July 2019 A search for counterparts to ANITA neutrino candidates with IceCube, International Cosmic-ray Conference, Madison, WI

#### **Posters**

- July 2020 Constraining Astrophysical interpretations of ANITA events with IceCube, Neutrino2020 (virtual, poster)
- July 2019 Searches for neutrinos from fast radio bursts with IceCube, International Cosmic-ray Conference, Madison WI
- July 2019 Particle Identification in Smartphone Camera Images Using the Distributed Electronic Cosmic-ray Observatory, International Cosmic-ray Conference, Madison WI

#### **Peer-Reviewed Publications**

### Major Contributions or contributing author

ICECUBE collaboration, Follow-up of astrophysical transients in real time with the IceCube Neutrino Observatory, 2012.04577

Accepted for publication in the Astrophysical Journal.

ICECUBE collaboration, A search for IceCube events in the direction of ANITA neutrino candidates, Astrophys. J. 892 (2020) 1 [2001.01737]

I. Safa, A. Pizzuto, C. A. Argüelles, F. Halzen, R. Hussain, A. Kheirandish et al., *Observing EeV neutrinos through the Earth: GZK and the anomalous ANITA events*, *JCAP* **2001** (2020) 012 [1909.10487]

#### Significant contributions

ICECUBE collaboration, *IceCube Search for Neutrinos Coincident with Compact Binary Mergers from LIGO-Virgo's First Gravitational-wave Transient Catalog, Astrophys. J. Lett.* **898** (2020) L10 [2004.02910]

ICECUBE collaboration, A Search for MeV to TeV Neutrinos from Fast Radio Bursts with IceCube, Astrophys. J. **890** (2019) [1908.09997]

#### Complete list of publications

Contributing author on all IceCube Collaboration papers since June 2018, for a complete list of publications, see (1)

# **Conference Proceedings**

A. Pizzuto, A. Barbano, T. Montaruli and J. Vandenbroucke, A search for IceCube events in the direction of ANITA neutrino candidates, in 36th International Cosmic Ray Conference (ICRC 2019) Madison, Wisconsin, USA, July 24-August 1, 2019, 2019, 1908.08060

A. Kheirandish, A. Pizzuto and J. Vandenbroucke, Searches for neutrinos from fast radio bursts with IceCube, in ICRC 2019 Madison, Wisconsin, USA, July 24-August 1, 2019, 2019, 1909.00078

- A. Pizzuto, J. Vandenbroucke, B. Gallay, M. Meehan, J. Bourbeau, J. Peacock et al., Particle Identification in Smartphone Camera Images Using the Distributed Electronic Cosmic-ray Observatory, in ICRC 2019 Madison, Wisconsin, USA, July 24-August 1, 2019, 2019
- J. Vandenbroucke, A. Pizzuto and K. Meagher, *IceCube as a Multi-messenger Follow-up Observatory for Astrophysical Transients*, in *ICRC 2019 Madison, Wisconsin, USA, July 24-August 1, 2019*, 2019, 1909.05834